<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<memo url="icann">
  <title>What has the US done with the Internet?</title>
  <date year="2016" month="October" day="07" />
  <img>https://emilyshepherd.me/images/icann.png</img>

  <description>
    US Government ends its 18 year oversight over ICANN
  </description>

  <content>
    <section>
      <p>
        Something interesting happened at the start of this month: the 
        US Government finally relinquished its power over ICANN, the 
        organisation in charge of "The Internet". There have been a lot 
        of fairly animated reactions to this news, and I can understand 
        why; this sounds like a big deal, no? Well, yes and no, allow me 
        to explain...
      </p>

      <p>
        First of all, we need to understand what ICANN actually is and 
        what it does. Above, I said that it controls "The Internet" and 
        I made sure to put that in quotes. I did that because it's not 
        really true, unfortunately when it comes to the Internet, 
        nothing is quite that simple. ICANN does the job of IANA, the 
        Internet Assigned Numbers Authority, which is a body set up way 
        back in 1988.
      </p>

      <p>So, ICANN manages IANA? Ok, Emily... what does IANA do?</p>
      
      <p>
        Great question, reader! Well, IANA is responsible for a bunch of 
        useful things, which can be split into three categories:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>IP Addresses</li>
        <li>Domain Names</li>
        <li>Protocol Assignments</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        IP Addresses can be thought of as the post codes, or phone 
        numbers, to the Internet. Every computer on the Internet has one 
        and they can use these to "ring up" each other to send data 
        between themselves <ref to="RFC791" />. IANA is the authority in 
        charge of handing these IP addresses out, like the post office 
        might hand out post codes <ref to="IANA-NUMBERS" />. IANA 
        doesn't do this directly, however, instead it hands out massive 
        blocks of IP Address to the five Regional Internet Registries 
        (RIRs) who in turn hand out those IP addresses to companies.
      </p>

      <p>
        This brings us to domain names. Say I want to do a Google 
        search, how does my computer know what computer to "call up"?
        Google's IP address happens to be 216.58.201.14, but I don't 
        type that into my browser, I type "www.google.com" (which is a 
        lot nicer!). That's known as a domain name, and it's powered by 
        the domain name system; the Internet's "phone book" <ref 
          to="RFC1034" />.  Again, IANA manages this by delegating 
        authority out to other organisations <ref to="IANA-DNSROOT" />.  
        For example, all ".com" domains are managed by Verisign <ref 
          to="DOTCOM" /> and all ".uk" domains are managed by Nominet 
        <ref to="DOTUK" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        The third section is a little different. On the Internet, there 
        are lots and lots (and lots, and lots, and lots...) of 
        protocols, methods by which computers may communicate. When you 
        access a web page, for example, you use the Hyper Text Transfer 
        Protocol (HTTP) <ref to="RFC2616" />. If that channel were 
        encrypted, that'd be the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol 
        <ref to="RFC5246" />. There are protocols for everything: email, 
        Skype, printers, gaming, time, file transfer, instant messaging, 
        system monitoring, etc... IANA keeps a central database of these 
        protocols and their various settings and details <ref 
          to="IANA-ASSIGNMENTS" /> <ref to="RFC5226" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        That's quite the whistle-stop tour I've given there, but it 
        gives a broad overview of what IANA (and by extension, ICANN) 
        does.  The Internet is a massively distributed network, and 
        everyone pretty much does their own thing on it for the most 
        part. But, like all things, some degree of centralisation is 
        required, and IANA fulfils that requirement.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Where does the US fit into this?">
      <p>
        Like all good stories, to answer this we have to start at the 
        beginning: the birth of the Internet. The word "Inter-Net" 
        literally means "Between Networks" and that actually gives us a 
        hint how it all started out. No one woke up one day and said 
        "Hey, I want to create a thing that'll have emails and Facebook 
        on it, and I'll call it the Internet". Instead it sprang up from 
        various various bodies linking up their pre-existing computer 
        networks. One such example of this was ARPANET, a network 
        between certain academic bodies and the US Department of 
        Defence linking up their pre-existing computer networks <ref 
          to="ARPANET" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        In its infancy, it didn't have that many computers on it, so 
        didn't really need any complicated system of allocating IP 
        addresses and domain names, so it was all handled by one man, 
        Jon Postel, who was later jokingly referred to as the 'God of 
        the Internet' <ref to="ISOC-JONPOSTEL" /> <ref 
          to="BBC-JONPOSTEL" />. As the size of the Internet grew, so 
        did this task, and in 1988 that IANA was officially formed <ref 
          to="RFC1083" />, with Jon as its chair <ref to="RFC2468" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        Here's where a bit of a nuance comes in: where did IANA get its 
        authority from? Who allowed it to be the central authority for 
        the Internet? Who <em>owned</em> the Internet? An early academic 
        document suggested IANA performed its function on behalf of the 
        IAB (Internet Activities Board; an independent body of 
        researchers) <ref to="RFC1083" /> however the US seemed to 
        believe it fell under an Internet research contract between the 
        Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency and the Information 
        Sciences Institute (the ISI), where Jon worked <ref 
          to="DNSDRAFT"/>.  This contract, however, was formed in 1988, 
        and Jon had been managing IPs and domain names since 1972.  This 
        contract involved a research grant to the ISI; could such a deal 
        retroactively assume authority over IANA?
      </p>

      <p>
        The other area of interest is the root nameservers, the physical 
        computers which host the Domain Name System. There were 12 of 
        these, three of which were operated directly by the US 
        Government (NASA, the Department of Defence and the Ballistic 
        Research Lab), the primary name server (server 'A') was managed 
        by Network Solutions, under contract from the National Science 
        Foundation, another government body. This primary name server 
        acted as the authority for the other 11, giving the US 
        Government direct control over the entire root 'zone'. The 
        remaining 8 servers, however, were run by independent, 
        non-governmental organisations.
      </p>

      <p>
        So it isn't clear who 'owned' the Internet. Don't forget that 
        this was an organic and open ended project, so as jobs need 
        doing, people start doing them and over time they become the de 
        facto authority, like Jon Postel did as head of IANA. Authority 
        over the Internet was in equilibrium between the US Government 
        (with its generous research grants and control over the root 
        zone) and the brains (IANA and the IAB).
      </p>

      <p>
        Such peace never lasts. In 1997, under the Clinton 
        administration, discussions were beginning to start about 
        whether the US' dominant position within the Internet was still 
        appropriate <ref to="DOC-RFC" />, given how much it had grown 
        internationally and within the private sector. It was at this 
        time that Jon did something crazy; he messaged the 
        administrators of the 8 non-governmental root nameservers and 
        ordered them to stop treating Network Solution's Server 'A' as 
        the primary, and switch to IANA's server instead. Amazingly, 
        they complied without question, accepting Jon's word the 
        ultimate authority when it came to DNS. This created a split in 
        the root servers, with 8 treating IANA's server as the primary 
        authority, and 4 treating server A as the primary <ref 
          to="WASHPO" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        Unsurprisingly, the US were not happy with this whatsoever and 
        ordered this change be immediately reversed, which it was. They 
        recognised the need to formalise the management model of the 
        domain name system to ensure such stunts couldn't happen again.  
        They also appreciated the need for a structure which could deal 
        with the increasingly commercial use of the Internet, and one 
        that could deal with trademark concerns.  For this reason, 
        therefore, the National Telecommunications and Information 
        Administration, within the Department of Commerce, moved to set 
        up ICANN which was contracted to perform IANA's functions <ref 
          to="DNSDRAFT" />.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section title="So ICANN was independent from the start?">
      <p>
        Kind of. While it was true that ICANN was largely in charge of 
        IANA, they were still "under contract" with the US and that 
        contract gave the government a decent amount of power and 
        oversight. The plan right from the start, however, was to 
        attempt to step back this oversight over time and let ICANN 
        manage itself.  The original plan even went as far as to state 
        that "The US Government would [be]...  phasing out as soon as 
        possible and in no event later than September 30, 2000" <ref 
          to="DNSDRAFT" />.  In 1999, however, this contract was 
        extended for a further four years, with the option of being 
        extended even further <ref to="NTIA-VERISIGN" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        Since 2000 the government <em>has</em> been making an effort to 
        scale back its involvement. For example, the original setup 
        involved both a contract relating to the IANA functions and a 
        document known as a 'Memorandum of Understanding' (MoU for 
        short), relating to ICANN's role in what they called the "DNS 
        Project".  This MoU gave the US Government a large stake in not 
        only the oversight of DNS, but also in active policy making and 
        consultation with foreign governments <ref to="MOU" />. In 2009, 
        this was lapsed and replaced with a far more wishy washy 
        "Affirmation of Commitments" <ref to="AOC" />. This was a big 
        deal and it effectively ended the US Government's legal claim 
        and involvement in the DNS Project <ref to="ALMOST-FREE" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        Over the following years, the US has been working further 
        towards this goal of true independence for ICANN. In 2012, for 
        example, the House Concurrent Resolution 127/Senate Concurrent 
        Resolution 50 told the Department of Commerce to "continue 
        working to implement the position of the United Sates on 
        Internet governance that clearly articulates the consistent and 
        unequivocal policy of the United States to promote a global 
        Internet free from government control and preserve and advance 
        the successful multi-stakeholder model that governs the Internet 
        today" <ref to="HCR127" />. This was reiterated again in 2013 
        under the House Resolution 1580 <ref to="HR1580" />.
      </p>

      <p>
        Finally, in 2014, the NTIA announced that it intended to allow 
        its contract with ICANN to lapse at its expiry at the end of 
        2015 <ref to="NTIA-EXP" />. The NTIA called for ICANN and the 
        community to present an acceptable plan to ensure the board 
        remain accountable to Internet Community. And that's what we've 
        been working towards for the last two years. The contract was 
        extended for a year last year because work wasn't quite ready, 
        but in March of this year, the proposals were finally complete.  
        The NTIA felt the proposals were acceptable and agreed to allow 
        the contract expire without renewal at the end of the year.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="What have we got now">
      <p>
        From ICANN's day-to-day point of view, not an enormous amount 
        will actually change; it will carry on doing its job and it will 
        carry on being guided by the community. The only real difference 
        is that it no longer needs to seek permission from the NTIA 
        whenever it wants to make changes to the root zone.
      </p>

      <p>
        Of course, the step back of the US Government would not be 
        sensible if they weren't assured that alternative oversight was 
        in place. Therefore, a new body has been created, the Empowered 
        Community (the EC) which has certain executive powers over ICANN 
        such as rejecting budgets and bylaw changes or recalling one or 
        more members of the board <ref to="BYLAW" />. The EC is made up 
        of representatives from ICANN's pre-existing Supporting 
        Organisations and Advisory Committees, namely:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>The Country-Code Names Supporting Organisation</li>
        <li>The Generic Names Supporting Organisation</li>
        <li>The Address Supporting Organisation</li>
        <li>The Root Server System Advisory Committee</li>
        <li>The Security and Stability Advisory Committee</li>
        <li>The Governmental Advisory Committee</li>
        <li>The At-Large Community</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        When it comes to the nomination of directors, the seats on the 
        Board are split such that the three Supporting Organisations 
        have two seats each, the At Large Community has one seat and the 
        remaining 8 seats are nominated by a special purpose "Nominating 
        Committee". The EC then has the final approval over each and 
        every director. (The only slight exception to this is the 
        President, who occupies seat 16 on the board and is appointed 
        directly by the board itself).
      </p>

      <p>
        On top of this, the changes have brought in three new committees 
        of interest: the Customer Standing Committee (CSC), the IANA 
        Naming Function Review (INFR) and the Independent Review Process 
        (IRP). The CSC's function is to act as a point of complaint 
        direct customers of the domain name system, the IRP was setup to 
        keep an overview of IANA post-transition away from the US 
        Government; based on IANA's performance, it has the authority to 
        recommend major changes to the Board to keep things running 
        smoothly. Finally, the Independent Review Process is the 'final 
        resort' fail safe if all of ICANN fails to abide by its own 
        ByLaws and procedures.
      </p>

      <p>
        It seems fair to conclude, therefore, that ICANN is now firmly 
        in the hands of the major stake-holders of the Internet; that 
        is, the people who use it! This transition, which was on the 
        cards ever since the inception of ICANN, has been the result of 
        a lot of hard work from the Internet Community over the last two 
        years, and has been on the cards since ICANN's formation; onto 
        ICANN's next challenge, I say!
      </p>
    </section>
  </content>

  <references>
    <reference id="RFC791">
      <title>Internet Protocol</title>
      <date month="September" year="1981" />
      <author>Information Sciences Institute</author>
      <url>https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc791.txt</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="IANA-NUMBERS">
      <title>Number Resources</title>
      <author>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</author>
      <url>https://www.iana.org/numbers</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="RFC1034">
      <title>DOMAIN NAMES - CONCEPTS AND FACILITIES</title>
      <author>Mockapetris, P.</author>
      <date month="November" year="1987" />
      <url>https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1034.txt</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="DOTCOM">
      <title>.com Registry Agreement</title>
      <date day="1" month="December" year="2012" />
      <author>ICANN, Verisign Inc.</author>
      <url>
        https://www.icann.org/resources/pages/agreement-2012-12-05-en
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="DOTUK">
      <title>Nominet UK - History</title>
      <author>Nominet</author>
      <url>
        https://web.archive.org/web/20020602051251/www.nominet.org.uk/nominet/about/history.html
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="RFC2616">
      <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</title>
      <author>
        Fielding, R., Gettys, J., Mogul, J., Frystyk, H., Masinter, L., 
        Leach, P., and T. Berners-Lee
      </author>
      <date month="June" year="1999" />
      <url>http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2616</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="RFC5246">
      <title>
        The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2
      </title>
      <author>Dierks, T. and Rescorla, E.</author>
      <date month="August" year="2008" />
      <url>https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5246</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="IANA-DNSROOT">
      <title>Domain Name Services</title>
      <author>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</author>
      <url>https://www.iana.org/domains</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="IANA-ASSIGNMENTS">
      <title>Protocol Registries</title>
      <author>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</author>
      <url>https://www.iana.org/numbers</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="RFC5226">
      <title>
        Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs
      </title>
      <author>Narten, T. and Alvestrand, H.</author>
      <date month="May" year="2008" />
      <url>https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5226</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="DNSDRAFT">
      <title>
        A PROPOSAL TO IMPROVE TECHNICAL MANAGEMENT OF INTERNET NAMES AND 
        ADDRESSES
      </title>

      <date year="1998" month="January" day="1" />

      <author>
        National Telecommunications and Information Administration
      </author>

      <url>
        https://web.archive.org/web/19980207224402/www.ntia.doc.gov/ntiahome/domainname/dnsdrft.htm
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="ARPANET">
      <title>ARPANET - The First Internet</title>
      <author>Living Internet</author>
      <url>http://www.livinginternet.com/i/ii_arpanet.htm</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="ISOC-JONPOSTEL">
      <title>In Memory of Jon Postel</title>
      <author>Rickard, W.</author>
      <date month="February" year="2009" />
      <url>
        http://www.internetsociety.org/articles/memory-jon-postel
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="BBC-JONPOSTEL">
      <title>Sci/Tech 'God of the Internet' is Dead</title>
      <author>BBC News</author>
      <date day="19" month="October" year="1988" />
      <url>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/196487.stm</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="RFC2468">
      <title>I Remember IANA</title>
      <author>Cerf, V.</author>
      <date month="October" year="1998" />
      <url>https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2468</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="RFC1083">
      <title>IAB Official Protocol Standards</title>
      <author>Internet Actives Board</author>
      <date month="December" year="1988" />
      <url>https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1083</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="DOC-RFC">
      <url>
        https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-1997-07-02/pdf/97-17215.pdf
      </url>
      <title>
        Request for Comments on the Registration and Administration of 
        Internet Domain Names
      </title>
      <author>Department of Commerce</author>
      <date day="2" month="July" year="1997" />
    </reference>

    <reference id="WASHPO">
      <url>http://songbird.com/pab/mail/0472.html</url>
      <title>
        Internet Reconfiguration Concerns Federal Officials
      </title>
      <author>Chandrasekaran, R.</author>
      <date day="31" month="January" year="1998" />
    </reference>

    <reference id="NTIA-VERSIGN">
      <title>Verisign Cooperative Agreement</title>
      <author>
        National Telecommunications and Information Administration,
        Verisign Inc, and ICANN
      </author>
      <url>
        http://www.ntia.doc.gov/page/verisign-cooperative-agreement
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="MOU">
      <title>
        Memorandum of Understanding Between the U.S. Department of 
        Commerce and the Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and 
        Numbers
      </title>
      <author>
        National Telecommunications and Information Administration, 
        ICANN
      </author>
      <date year="1998" month="November" />
      <url>
        http://www.ntia.doc.gov/page/1998/memorandum-understanding-between-us-department-commerce-and-internet-corporation-assigned-
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="AOC">
      <title>
        AFFIRMATION OF COMMITMENTS BY THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF 
        COMMERCE AND THE INTERNET CORPORATION FOR ASSIGNED NAMES AND 
        NUMBERS
      </title>
      <author>
        National Telecommunications and Information Administration, 
        ICANN
      </author>
      <date year="2009" month="September" />
    </reference>

    <reference id="ALMOST-FREE">
      <title>
        Almost Free: An Analysis of ICANN's ‘Affirmation of Commitments’
      </title>
      <author>Froomkin, A.</author>
      <date year="2011" month="January" day="20" />
      <url>
        http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1744086
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="HCR127">
      <title>
        Expressing the sense of Congress regarding actions to        
        preserve and advance the multi-stakeholder governance model 
        under which the Internet has thrived.
      </title>

      <date year="2012" month="May" day="30" />

      <author>US Congress</author>

      <url>https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/BILLS-112hconres127ih/pdf/BILLS-112hconres127ih.pdf</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="HR1580">
      <title>
        To affirm the policy of the United States regarding Internet 
        governance
      </title>

      <date year="2013" month="April" day="14" />

      <author>US House of Representatives</author>

      <url>https://www.congress.gov/bill/113th-congress/house-bill/1580</url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="NTIA-EXP">
      <title>
        NTIA Announces Intent to Transition Key Internet Domain Name 
        Functions
      </title>
      <author>
        National Telecommunications and Information Administration
      </author>
      <date day="14" month="March" year="2014" />
      <url>
        http://www.ntia.doc.gov/press-release/2014/ntia-announces-intent-transition-key-internet-domain-name-functions
      </url>
    </reference>

    <reference id="BYLAW">
      <title>
        BYLAWS FOR INTERNET CORPORATION FOR ASSIGNED NAMES AND NUMBERS A 
        California Nonprofit Public-Benefit Corporation
      </title>
      <date day="27" month="May" year="2016" />
      <author>ICANN</author>
      <url>
        https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/adopted-bylaws-27may16-en.pdf
      </url>
    </reference>
  </references>
</memo>
